Altitude 2,400. Speed 28,000. Relative to Earth.
Leaving Earth atmosphere. Switching to space speed 2.
Can we really save Earth?
Getting cold feet, Tactical Officer?
It's not like that...
Ship off our starboard bow. It's a friendly.
"We pray for your safe journey."
（ナレーション）＜西暦２１９９年＞
＜地球は
ガミラスとの戦いに敗れ→
人類滅亡まで
あと１年と迫っていた＞
＜国連宇宙軍は　ひそかに
恒星間宇宙船　ヤマトを開発＞
＜大マゼラン銀河にある惑星
イスカンダルに→
地球環境の再生システムを
受け取りに行くのである＞
＜宇宙戦艦ヤマトは　ついに→
１６万８０００光年の
大航海へと旅立った＞
（太田）
高度２４００。　対地速度２万８０００。
（島）地球大気圏　離脱。
第二宇宙速度　切り替える。
（古代進）
この地球を救えるんだろうか…。
（島）自信がないのか？　戦術長。
そんなんじゃない。
（森雪）右舷前方に　艦影。
友軍です。
（相原）「貴艦ノ健闘ト
航海ノ　無事ヲ祈ル」。
（沖田十三）
本艦は　これより　月軌道を抜け→
We will now pass through lunar orbit, and head for Mars, at cruising speed.
（通信）
巡航速度で　火星軌道に向かう。→
火星宙域に達した後→
Upon arrival, main staff are to gather in the central operations room.
メインスタッフは
中央作戦室に集合。
There will be a briefing on the warp test. That is all.
ワープテストの
ブリーフィングを行う。
以上だ。
（通信）こちら　着弾観測隊。
テロンの宇宙船が→
This is the impact observation team. A Teron ship has left orbit.
衛星軌道を離脱します。
（シュルツ）うむ…。
（ガンツ）艦隊を差し向けますか？
Should we send the fleet?
（シュルツ）いや　様子を見る。
えっ？
No, let's see what it does.
What does an inferior race, who cannot even leave their own solar system,
（シュルツ）太陽系を出ることすら
ままならぬ　劣等種族が→
plan to do with a single ship?
たった１隻で
何をたくらむのか…→
I'd like to watch and find out.
それを見極めるのだ。
諸君　イスカンダルへの旅は→
Men, the journey to Iscandar and back would take 336,000 years, at light speed.
光の速度で航行しても→
往復　３３万６０００年という時間を→
費やすものとなる。
それを　我々は
１年という　限りある時間の中で→
And we must complete that voyage within a single year.
消化しなくてはならない。
To do this, we require faster-than-light warp navigation,
そのためには
光速の壁を突破する→
超光速ワープ航法が　必要なのだ。
capable of breaking the light barrier.
A warp functions by generating an artificial wormhole,
（真田）ワープとは
このように　ワームホールを→
人為的に発生させ→
実質的に
光速を超える航法です。
that allows travel beyond the speed of light.
（徳川）わしには
よく分からんが→
I don't fully understand this, but is it even possible?
本当に　そんなことが
できるのかね？
理論上は　可能です。→
Theoretically, yes.
ただ　タイミングを違えると→
But if you botch the timing, you'll create a space-time continuum distortion,
時空連続体に　ゆがみを生み→
and phase transition the universe itself.
宇宙そのものを
相転移させてしまうことも→
ありえる。
というと　つまり…。
Meaning what, in practice?
That we must be very careful with the Wave Motion Engine.
それだけ
波動エンジンの運用には→
細心の注意が必要だということだ。
自信がないのか？　航海長。
Getting cold feet, Navigation Officer?
（島）そんなんじゃない。
（真田）それと　もう一つ。
It's not like that.
And one more thing.
（新見）
技術科　情報長の新見です。→
I am Niimi, the Engineering Intelligence Officer.
We have completed a weapon, capable of harnessing the Wave Motion Engine's
我々は　その波動エンジンの
莫大なエネルギーを応用した→
兵器を完成させ　ヤマト艦首に
搭載することに成功しました。
vast power, and have loaded it aboard the Yamato's bow.
A weapon?
兵器…　ですか？
The Dimensional Wave Motion Explosive Compression Emitter.
次元波動爆縮放射機。→
We call it the Wave Motion Gun for short.
便宜上
私たちは　波動砲と呼んでいます。
波動砲…。　どんな武器なんです？
The Wave Motion Gun? How does it work?
簡単に言えば
波動エンジン内で開放された→
Put simply,
it extends the higher dimensions,
expanded in the Wave Motion Engine, along its line of fire.
余剰次元を　射線上に展開。→
超重力で　形成された
マイクロブラックホールが→
The micro black holes created by supergravity release Hawking radiation.
瞬時に　ホーキング輻射を放ち…。
（南部）それって　この艦自体が
巨大な大砲ってことじゃ…。
So does that mean the entire ship is a giant cannon?
（新見）当たらずとも遠からずね。
（徳川）わしには　さっぱりじゃな。
Not quite, but close.
I don't understand at all.
Eventually, we'll need to test fire the Wave Motion Gun.
この波動砲も　いずれ　試射を
行わなくてはならないでしょう。
We'll test the warp in the low gravity interference area past Mars.
ワープテストは
火星軌道を越えた→
重力低干渉宙域にて行う。
The test is set for 0130. Everyone, suit up, just in case.
テスト予定時刻は　０１３０。
万一に備えて
全員　船外服を着用。　解散！
Dismissed!
Sasha is asleep on Mars, isn't she?
サーシャは
火星に眠っているのね。
たった独りで…。
All alone...
Please watch us. We will reach your homeland.
（心の声）≪見ていてください≫
≪僕たちは
あなたの故郷に　必ず行きます≫
≪はるか
１６万８０００光年のかなたから→
After a journey to Earth, of 168,000 light years, all alone.
たった独りで　地球を目指し→
その気の遠くなるような
長い旅路の果て→
A journey too long to even imagine...
You gave us the courage and hope to survive. We won't let that go to waste...
僕らに　生きる希望と
勇気を与えてくれた→
あなたの心に　必ず応えます≫
ん？
[ｽﾋﾟｰｶ]（機関員）
前進速度　１２エスノット…。
（薮）おやっさん
時空を曲げちまうなんて→
Chief, can we really bend space-time itself?
ほんとに　できるんですかね？
分からん→
No idea! Sometimes, you've just gotta try.
何事も　やってみんことにはな。
テスト開始　２分前。
Two minutes until test.
Confirm post-warp coordinates.
（島）ワープ明け座標軸　確認。
（太田）確認した。→
Confirmed.
天王星軌道　Ｆ８６３０の空間点。
Point S8630, in Uranus's orbit. Coordinate axis set.
（島）座標軸　固定する。→
Increasing speed, from 12 to 33 s-knots.
速度
１２から　３３エスノットに増速。
Increase engine output.
（徳川・通信）両舷　増速。　出力→
Raise output from 40 to 99.
４０から　９９まで上げ。→
波動エンジン　室圧上昇中。
Wave Motion Engine internal pressure rising.
（太田）速度　３０エスノット！→
Speed is 30 s-knots...
３３エスノット！
33 s-knots!
[ｽﾋﾟｰｶ]　テスト開始　１分前。
（佐渡）いや～→
One minute until test.
船は出ていく　ケムリは残る→
The ship sets sail and the smoke stays behind
残るケムリが
シャクの種～ときたぁ…→
The smoke that stays behind causes the throat to ache.
There we go! It's time!
あっ　あっ！　ぐっときたよ～！
（西川）
いくら　家がお寺さんだからって…。
Even if he does come from a family of priests, that chant is still pretty morbid.
（篠原）
なんか　もう　おしまいって感じ。
（加藤）色不異空　空不異色！
Speed is 36 s-knots!
（太田）速度　３６エスノット！
秒読みに入ります。　１０→
Commencing countdown.
10.
９　８　７→
9-
8-
7-
6-
６　５　４→
5-
4-
３　２　１！
3-
2-
1-
（島）ワープ！
Warp!
やった！
Yes!
はぁ…。　あっ！
（島）はっ！
こ…　ここは…。
Where are we?
Jupiter...
（真田）木星!?
なんで…。
Why?
Hey, Shima!
おい　島！
航海長　状況　知らせ！
Navigation Officer, report!
わ…　分かりません！
時空座標の設定では→
I-I don't know...
The space-time coordinates were right...
確かに…。
（真田）予定ルート上に→
An unknown obstacle was detected in our path.
未知の障害物を感知。
回避したのかもしれません。
It may have been an attempt to avoid it.
（太田）ヤマト
木星の重力場に　捕まっています！
The Yamato is caught in Jupiter's gravity field!
ダメだ…
どんどん引き寄せられていく。
It's no good. It's drawing us in...
I can't control the ship!
（島）舵が利きません！
うろたえるな！
Stay calm!
Engine room, report.
機関室　状況を報告せよ。
The main engine isn't transferring energy correctly.
（徳川）主エンジンから
エネルギーがうまく回らんのです。
I'll try switching to sub-engines.
補助エンジンに切り替えて
やってみます。
補助エンジンに動力伝達。
安定翼　展開！
Power flowing to the sub-engines.
Deploying stabilizer wings.
頼むぞ　島。
分かってる！
Take care of it, Shima.
I know!
レーダーに感あり。
前方　６万５０００キロ。
I'm seeing something on radar. 65,000 kilometers away.
Not a ship. It's too big!
艦ではありません。　大きすぎます。
Magnify.
拡大投影。
（真田）赤外線映像に切り替え。
Switching to infrared.
これは…。
That's...
That floating object is nearly the size of Australia.
（太田）この浮遊物体は
ほぼ　オーストラリア大陸と→
同程度の面積を
持っているもようです。
Shima, soft land the Yamato on the floating continent.
島　この浮遊大陸に
ヤマトを軟着陸させろ。
了解！
Roger!
くっ！
（島）ぐっ…。
島　もう少しだ！
Shima, almost there!
錨　打ち込め！
（太田）打てぇ！
Fire anchor!
Fire!
はぁ…。
（徳川・通信）艦長→
Captain, we've located the cause of the engine trouble.
エンジントラブルの原因が
分かりました。
主エンジンの冷却器が
オーバーヒートしとります。
The main engine's coolant system is overheating.
Understood.
分かった。　すぐ修理にかかれ。
Begin repairs immediately.
古代君　甲板部から
船外作業班を編成して→
Kodai, put a team together from the deck crew, and go collect samples.
サンプル採取に当たってくれ。
はい。
Yes, sir!
AU09, it's your turn to shine.
ＡＵ０９　出番よ。
（ＡＵ０９）
番号ナンカデ呼ブナ！→
Don't call me by number.
I am a free unit.
私ハ　自由ナ　ゆにっとダ。
（相原・南部）ええ～!?
This thing is autonomous?
こいつ　自立型だったのか。
（真田）ＡＵ０９。　ヤマトの
自立型サブコンピューターだ。
AU09, the Yamato's autonomous sub-computer.
（ＡＵ０９）
「アナライザー」ト呼ンデクダサイ。
Call me Analyzer.
Daddy, finish your work soon, and come home, okay?
（ヒルデ）お父さん　お仕事
早く終わらせて帰って来てね。→
お母さんも　お父さんを心配…。
（ガンツ・通信）シュルツ司令。
Mom's worried...
Commander Shultz...
What is it, Ganz?
どうした？　ガンツ。
はっ。
A message from Larleta, at the Floating Continent base.
浮遊大陸基地の
ラーレタから報告が。
第５惑星ズピストのか？
はい。　その大陸に→
From planet five, Zupist?
Yes. The Teron ship has landed there.
例のテロン艦が
着陸したとのことです。
バカな。
ヤツは　まだ　内惑星系を→
Ridiculous...
It should still be wandering the inner solar system.
うろついてるはずだ。
（ガンツ）それが→
Well, apparently, they have also seen traces of a Geschtam Jump.
ゲシュタムジャンプの空間航跡も→
観測されておりまして。
Impossible.
まさか　ヤツが
ジャンプしたとでも言うのか!?
Are you trying to tell me they jumped?
I couldn't say for certain...
（ガンツ）いえ　それは　なんとも…。
んん…。→
浮遊大陸基地の艦艇は？
What of the Floating Continent's fleet?
（ガンツ・通信）補給基地ですので
現在　４隻程度です。
It's a resupply base. Presently, only four ships are there.
（シュルツ）それでいい。　その戦力で
ラーレタに　たたかせろ。
That will be sufficient.
Have Larleta use those ships to destroy them.
（ガンツ）はっ！
Yes, sir.
（ラーレタ）分かりました。　直ちに→
Understood.
I shall dispatch the combat fleet immediately.
戦闘艦艇を向かわせます。
ニャー
Teron weapons cannot pierce our armor.
（ラーレタ）テロンの武器では
こちらの装甲を　貫通できません。
Four is practically overkill.
４隻でも　多いくらいです。
（遠山）植物採集なんて
小学生みたいなんだな。
Hunting for plants... Feels like I'm back in elementary school.
Stop whining.
（榎本）ぶつくさ言うな！　ん？
Temperature and pressure are far different than on Jupiter's surface.
（ＡＵ０９）気温　大気圧トモニ
木星表面トハ　著シク異ナル。
大気成分　メタン６７％→
Atmospheric composition: Methane 67%.
窒素６％　二酸化炭素２１％。→
Nitrogen 6%. Carbon dioxide 21%.
Detecting acetaldehyde and ethanol, as well.
（通信）大気中ニ　アセトアルデヒド
オヨビ　エタノールヲ検出。
（相原）アルコールかぁ。
（太田）そういや俺　なんだか…→
Alcohol, huh?
Come to think of it, I'm kinda...
ううっ！
うわぁ～！　あっ…。
Warp sickness, huh?
（佐渡）こりゃあ　ワープ酔いじゃな。
（加藤）なんすか？　それ…。
What's that?
まあ　二日酔いみたいなもんじゃよ。
Like a hangover.
飲むか？　迎え酒。
（加藤）い…　いえ…。
Want a drink, to dull the pain?
I'll pass...
（ＡＵ０９）地球ニ繁殖シテイル
未知ノ異星植物トノ→
DNA match with unknown, extraterrestrial plants now living on Earth is 99.98%.
ＤＮＡ適合率　９９．９８％デス。
In other words, this environment was imported, from outside the solar system.
（真田）つまり
この環境は　太陽系外から→
人為的に　持ち込まれたものだ
ということです。
将来　地球を
ガミラスフォーミングするため→
They moved this entire continent to Jupiter, to aid in gamilasforming Earth.
大陸ごと　木星に
移植したものと考えられます。
Then there should be...
だとすると　ここには…。
レーダーに感あり！
Ships on radar!
Gamilas vessels.
ガミラス艦です！
全艦　戦闘態勢！
All crew to battle stations!
主砲　発射準備！
（島）だが　古代→
Prepare to fire main guns.
But, Kodai, until the main engine is fixed, we can't route energy to the guns!
機関の修理が終わらなければ
主砲に　エネルギーを回せないぞ。
The Type-3 rounds are bullets. We can fire them.
（南部）三式弾なら　実体弾なので
射撃可能です。
The Type-3 are for short range!
三式は　射程が短い！
ショックカノンなら
ロングレンジでも　たたけるのに。
If we had shock cannons, we could shoot them from a distance.
（真田）艦長　バイパスを通せば
ショックカノンも→
Captain, we could use a bypass to fire a few rounds from the shock cannons.
数発は　撃てるはずです。
うむ…。
The repairs will be done in five minutes. Can you hold out that long?
（徳川・通信）修理は
あと５分ほどで終わります。
それまで　なんとかなりませんか？
事態は　一刻を争うのだ。
There's no time. Connect the bypass.
バイパスをつなげ。
主砲に　動力伝達。
Route power to main guns. Ready Type-3 artillery in secondary guns!
三式弾は　副砲に装填して　待機。
Energy transferred to main guns. We can fire shock cannons!
（南部）主砲　エネルギー　来ました。
ショックカノン　撃てます！
１番　２番は
左舷の　先行する駆逐艦を狙え。
One and two, aim for the destroyers approaching on port side.
３番は　後方から回り込んでくる
戦艦をたたく。
Three, prepare to fire at the ship circling around from aft.
Target locked. Auto-tracking enabled.
目標を捕捉した。　自動追尾よし。
撃ち方　始め！
ビシュン！　ビシュン！
Open fire!
ドーーン！
ビシュン！
左舷　魚雷接近！
Torpedoes approaching from port!
AA defenses!
対空防御。
Enemy torpedoes downed!
（太田）敵魚雷　排除！
（南部）敵艦　三式弾の射程に入った。
Enemy ships now within range of Type-3 rounds!
副砲　撃ち方　始め！
撃てぇ～！
Secondary guns, open fire.
Fire!
ドォン！
ガン　ガン　ガン！
ドーーン！
Enemy ship in retreat.
敵艦　撤退します！
（徳川・通信）こちら　機関室。
This is the engine room. Repairs complete.
修理　完了しました。
Activate engine. Raise anchor!
機関始動。　錨　上げ！
We're reaching the continent's edge!
（太田）大陸外縁部に達します。
（太田）
浮遊大陸との距離　２万３０００キロ。
We're 23,000 kilometers from the floating continent!
Kodai, fire Wave Motion Gun at the floating continent.
古代　波動砲で　浮遊大陸を撃て。
えっ…。
波動砲の試射を兼ねて→
We will test fire the Wave Motion Gun, and destroy the enemy base.
敵基地を　ここでたたく。
（真田）
波動砲の威力は　未知数です。→
We don't know how powerful the Wave Motion Gun is.
Without knowing possible effects, using it will be too risky.
効果が
不確定な状況下での使用は→
リスクが高すぎるのでは…。
（徳川）やってみようじゃないか→
Let's try it, Sanada.
真田君。　ここでダメだったら
先に行っても　ダメなんだ。
If we can't do it here, we won't be able to test it anywhere.
総員　準備にかかれ！
All crew, stand by to open fire.
取舵反転！
艦首を　浮遊大陸に向けよ。
Turn the ship around. Point bow at the floating continent.
（真田）
艦内の電源を　再起動時に備えて→
Switching ship to emergency power, in preparation for reboot.
非常用に　切り替える。
航海長　操艦を戦術長に回せ。
Navigation Officer, transfer control to Tactical Officer.
戦術長に回します。
戦術長　頂きました。
Transferring to Tactical Officer.
Tactical Officer has control.
森　大陸の熱源は？
Mori, what heat sources are visible on the continent?
大陸中心部の
盆地に集中しています。
They're concentrated in the basin, at the continent's center.
うむ　座標を送れ。　古代！
Send the coordinates... Kodai!
了解。　艦首を大陸中心に向けます。
Roger! Pointing bow at continent's center.
Open circuit to the Wave Motion Gun.
波動砲への回路　開け。
回路　開きます。　非常弁　全閉鎖。→
Opening circuit.
Sealing emergency vents. Activating force injector.
強制注入器　作動。
安全装置　解除。
セーフティーロック　解除。
Release safety lock.
Releasing safety lock.
Confirmed activation of force injector. Final safety released.
強制注入器　作動を確認。
最終セーフティー　解除。
Target scope open!
ターゲットスコープ　オープン。
薬室内　タキオン粒子　圧力上昇。→
Tachyon particle pressure rising in chamber.
８６　９７　１００→
86, 97, 100... Energy charge at 120%.
エネルギー充填　１２０％。
Floating continent is 23,000 kilometers off the bow. Relative speed 36.
浮遊大陸　艦首方向　２万３０００キロ。
相対速度　３６。
艦首　軸線に乗った。
Bow is level with firing axis.
照準　誤差修正　プラス２度。
Correct for target errors +2 degrees.
波動砲　発射用意。
Prepare to fire Wave Motion Gun.
対ショック　対閃光　防御。
Engage anti-shock and anti-flare defenses.
電影クロスゲージ　明度２０。
照準　固定。
Electronic cross-gauge, display brightness twenty. Target locked.
（南部）発射　１０秒前。　９→
Ten seconds until fire.
9-
8-
８　７　６→
7-
6-
５　４→
5-
4-
3-
３　２　１！
2-
1...
撃て！
Fire.
バシューー!!
（ラーレタ）ああっ！　なんです!?
一体　何が起きているの!?
What is this?
What in the world is happening?
ドォーーン!!
これが　波動砲…。
すごい武器だよ！
This is the Wave Motion Gun...
An amazing weapon!
これさえあれば　ガミラスと対等に
いや…　それ以上に戦える！
With this, we can fight the Gamilans on even terms...
No, we have the advantage!
いや　我々は
ガミラスの基地さえ潰せれば→
However, we only wanted to destroy the Gamilas base.
それで　よかったはずだ。→
しかし　波動砲は
大陸そのものを破壊してしまった。
But the Wave Motion Gun destroyed the entire continent.
Our objective isn't to exterminate the enemy.
我々の目的は
敵を　殲滅することではない。
The Yamato's weaponry exists solely for self-defense.
ヤマトの武器は
あくまで　身を守るためのものだ。
A power that could destroy the universe itself.
≪宇宙さえ　滅ぼしかねない力…≫
≪我々は　禁断のメギドの火を→
Have we attained the forbidden fire of Megiddo?
手にしてしまったのだろうか≫
≪いや　今は思うまい≫
No, I won't think of that now.
≪これが試しであるならば→
If this is a trial, we need only show the correct path in our actions.
我々は　その行動で　よき道を→
示していくだけなのだ≫
Episode 3: Escape from the Jupiter Sphere
The Wave Motion Gun...
Its terrifying power has damaged the Yamato itself.
A mysterious distress call...
Different feelings...
What will the man of the sea decide?
And Kodai sees a hero, who rests upon a frozen satellite.
A requiem sounds in empty space.
Next time: Gravestone on a Frozen Field.
There are 363 days left before humanity is extinct.
中国内陸部の四川省で
昨日発生したマグニチュード７．
０の地震だが、
死傷者の数は１万１０００人以上
に増え、
被災者の数は１５０万人以上にも
上っている。